Guide to the Larry Racioppo Photograph Collection 1999-2004 PR 208
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Larry Racioppo Photograph Collection
1999-2004
PR 208
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.75 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The Larry Racioppo Photograph Collection spans the period from 1999-2004 and contains color photographs taken by Racioppo. Most were commissioned by the New-York Historical Society in the wake of the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks, or for related exhibits at the Society in the following years.
Provenance
Most of the photographs were either commissioned by the New-York Historical Society or were printed for exhibition purposes. "Fireman's Funeral" was a gift of the photographer.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Larry Racioppo is a Brooklyn native and New York based photographer.
Scope and Content Note
The Larry Racioppo Photograph Collection spans the period from 1999-2004 and contains contact prints and color photographs taken by Racioppo. Most were commissioned by the New-York Historical Society in the wake of the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks, or for related exhibits at the Society in the following years. The collection is divided into two series: Contact Prints; Photographs.
Series I. Contact Prints are separated by format and sorted by subject. The 4 x 5 in. contact prints are further organized by numbers assigned by the photographer.
Subseries I. 4 x 5 IN. CONTACT PRINTS consist of thirty-five contact prints from 4 x 5 inch color negatives. Twenty-nine of these prints are images of the interior and exterior of St. Paul's Chapel, including memorials on surrounding fences. The other six prints are of the exterior and interior of the Rescue 2 firehouse. Large prints of many of these images can be found in Series II.
Subseries II. 8 x 10 IN. CONTACT SHEETS includes three contact sheets of photographs taken at the Rescue Company 2 firehouse. These images show the firehouse's interior and exterior.
Series II. Photographs is grouped by subject. One photograph shows the funeral of firefighter John Moran, who died in the September 11, 2001 terrorist attacks. Ten photographs show the interior and exterior of St. Paul's Chapel on Broadway during its use as a relief center after September 11, 2001. Several of these photographs are portraits of the relief workers who were employed at Ground Zero and the support staff at St. Paul's who tended to them and other visitors to the area. A group of eight photographs documents the interior and exterior of the building housing Rescue Two, a New York City Fire Department company in Brooklyn that sustained heavy losses on September 11, 2001. Nine photographs document churches in New York City that have been converted from theaters. They show how the congregations have adapted the interiors for religious use. The photographs range in size from 11 x 14 inches to 20 x 24 inches.
Arrangement
Photographs are divided into two series: Contact Prints and Photographs. They are further divided by subject. The 4 x 5 in. contact prints are also arranged by numbers assigned by the photographer.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other photographs of September 11, 2001-related topics can be found in the World Trade center Photograph Collection (PR 169), the Irwin Silver Photograph Collection (PR 209) and the Harry Tarzian Photograph Collection (PR 255). Other photographs of churches can be found throughout photograph collections in the Department.
Church buildings -- New york (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; Color photographs; Disaster relief -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; New York (N.Y.); Photographic prints; Portraits; Rescue work -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Pictorial works; St. Paul's Chapel -- Pictorial works; Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Contact Prints
  - 4 X 5 IN. CONTACT PRINTS
    - St. Paul's Chapel, exterior (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - St. Paul's Chapel, interior (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Rescue 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 8 X 10 IN. CONTACT SHEETS
    - Rescue 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rescue workers (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series II: Photographs
  - FUNERALS
    - Fireman's Funeral, Belle Harbor, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - ST. PAUL'S CHAPEL
    - 10 photos showing fence outside St. Paul's, workers inside, and the interior of the chapel with WTC-related items, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - RESCUE 2
    - 8 photographs of the Brooklyn fire company, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CHURCHES
    - First Corinthian Baptist Church (3 photos), 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mount Olivet Baptist Church (3 photos), 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Second Canaan Baptist Church (3 photos), 2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)